Troy, N.Y. United Calvary Congregational Church Records, 1906-2021.
Congregational Library & Archives
Troy, N.Y. United Calvary Congregational Church records, 1906-2021.
RG5420
Congregational Library & Archives
0.77 Cubic Feet
(2 boxes, 1 folder)
In 1906, the United Armenian Calvary Congregational Church formed under the moniker "Armenian Presbyterian Church of Troy." After the completion of a church building in 1914, the church was separated into the Presbyterian Church and "The Armenian Congregational Church of Troy, N.Y." which cooperated closely and worked out of the same church building. These churches were reunited in 1919 under their final name, The United Armenian Calvary Congregational Church, up until the church was closed in 2020. This collection records the activities and membership of this organization through church record books, membership records, photograph collections, and financial records.
United Armenian Calvary Congregational Church
Restrictions on Access
Access to this collection is unrestricted and open to the public.
Acquisition Information
Materials were donated to the Congregational Library & Archives by the United Armenian Calvary Congregational Church in March 2021; RG5420.
Historical Note
The beginning of The United Armenian Calvary Congregational Church in 1906 followed a wave of immigration from modern-day Turkey resulting from the Armenian massacres of 1895. The church formed under the moniker "Armenian Presbyterian Church of Troy", but after the completion of a church building in 1914, the church was separated into the Presbyterian Church and "The Armenian Congregational Church of Troy, N.Y." which cooperated closely and worked out of the same church building. These churches were reunited in 1919 under their final name, The United Armenian Calvary Congregational Church, up until the church was closed in 2020. The church operated a sunday school which focused on teaching about Armenian heritage and forming connections with Armenian communities throughout the United States. Every holiday and season, the church hosted a food kitchen in which feasts were prepared for its members. A list of the pastors who served the church follows:
Ministers
Rev. Sarkis O Kerian 1910-1911
Rev. Mihran T Kalaijian 1912-1918
Rev. Puzant Levonian 1918-1920
Rev. Samuel Rejebian 1920-1926
Rev. Ephraim Jernazian 1927-1940
Rev. Mihran Renjilian 1944-1959
Rev. Charles Baboian 1957-1965
Rev. Jirair Sogomian 1965-1968
Rev. Dennis Durgin 1968-1971
Rev. Vigen Galustian 1971-1975
Rev. Vincent Kumjian 1973-1978, 2005-2006
Rev. William Hammann 1978-1989
Rev. Joanne Gulezian-Hartunian 1989-1997
Rev. Munro Roberts 1998-1999
Rev. Stanley Skinner 1999-2000, 2002-2005
Rev. Mihran Kupeyian 2000-2002
Scope and Contents
The Troy, N.Y. United Calvary Congregational Church records include church record books, membership records, church correspondence, photograph collections, and anniversary reports. Also included are financial records, in the form of treasurer's records, receipts, and building records.
Arrangement
Materials have been arranged in chronological order by start date, and further by relation when appropriate.
Armenian massacres, 1894-1896.; Baptismal records.; Church buildings.; Church correspondence.; Church finance.; Church membership.; Church records and registers.; Marriage records.; Necrologies.; Photographs.; Obituaries.; United Armenian Calvary Congregational Church; Troy (N.Y.) -- Church history.
- Church records, 1906 1960; 1906-1960 (Box 1, Volume 1)
- Church records, 1927 1978; 1927-1978 (Box 2, Volume 2)
  Separated Materials
  Material was removed from this item and moved to "Materials from Church Records, 1927-1978"
- Materials from church records, 1927-1978, 1929 1942; 1929-1942 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  This material was taken from the item "Church Records, 1927-1978"
- Church records, 1976 2020; 1976-2020 (Box 2, Volume 1)
  Material was removed from this item and moved to "Materials from Church Records, 1976-2020"
- Materials from church records, 1976 2020; 1976-2020 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Church history, 1914 2020; 1914-2020 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- Photographs: groups, 1961 1990; 1961-1990 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Testimonial photographs, 1972 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Special event records, 1972 2001; 1972-2001 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Photographs: church gatherings, 1977 1991; 1977-1991 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Scrapbook, 1978 1992; 1978-1992 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- Financial records and by-laws, 1991 2021; 1991-2021 (Box 2, Folder 7)
- Building records, 2015 2020; 2015-2020 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- Closure worship service, 2020 (Box 2, Compact disk 1)
- Photographs: groups, undated (Folder 4)